<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="scheduler.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!--$Id$-->

<description
    title    = "HTTP Server und Web Services"
    base_dir = ""
    author   = "$Author$"
    date     = "$Date$"
>

    <scheduler_keyword keyword="HTTP Server"/>
    <scheduler_keyword keyword="HTML"/>
    
    
    <h2>Web Services</h2>
    <p>
        Der Job Scheduler kann die Ausführung von Jobs und Job-Ketten als Web Services kapseln.
        Dazu nimmt der Job Scheduler über den eingebauten HTTP-Server SOAP Anfragen entgegen.
    </p>
    <p>
        Mit <scheduler_element name="web_service"/> können Web Services eingerichtet werden.
    </p>
    <p>
        Verwendung und Beispiele zur Konfiguration sind in der Dokumentation  »Web Service Tutorial« beschrieben.
    </p>
    
    
    <h2>Bedienung über einen Browser</h2>
    <p>
        Der Job Scheduler verfügt über einen HTTP Server und stellt HTML-Seiten zu seiner Bedienung bereit.
        Sie können den Job Scheduler über einen Browser (Microsoft Internet Explorer und Firefox)
        steuern. Geben Sie z.B. die Adresse <code>http://localhost:4444</code> ein.
        <code>localhost</code> kann auch ein anderer Rechnername sein,
        und <code>4444</code> ist die konfigurierte TCP-Portnummer des Job Schedulers.
    </p>
    <p>
        Siehe <scheduler_element name="config" attribute="tcp_port"/>.<br/>
        Siehe <scheduler_ini_entry file="factory.ini" section="spooler" entry="html_dir"/>.<br/>
    </p>
		<p>
			The user interface is described in the 
			"<a href="user_interface">Built-In User Interface</a>" 
			section of this chapter (below).
		</p>
    
    
    <h2>Zugriffsschutz</h2>
    <p>
        Der Job Scheduler lässt nur TCP- und HTTP-Verbindung zu von Rechnern,
        die mit <scheduler_element name="allowed_host"/> die Erlaubnis bekommen haben.
    </p>
    <p>
        Darüber hinaus kann HTTP-Authentifizierung mit dem Element <scheduler_element name="http.authentication"/>
        vereinbart werden.
    </p>
    
    
    <scheduler_keyword keyword="Protokoll"/>
    
    <h2>Protokolle mit einem Browser zeigen</h2>
    <p>
        Während der Job Scheduler ein Protokoll schreibt, können Sie es sich anzeigen lassen.
        Sie sehen stets den neuesten Stand.
    </p>
    <p>
        Die HTML-Oberfläche des Job Schedulers bietet hierfür die entsprechenden Operationen an.
        Der Job Scheduler verwendet folgende URLs für Protokolle:
    </p>
    
    <p>
        <table cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0">
            <col valign="baseline"/>
            <col valign="baseline" style="padding-left: 2ex"/>
            <tr>
                <td>
                    Hauptprotokoll
                </td>
                <td>
                    <code>http://<i>localhost:4444</i>/show_log?</code>
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>
                    Jobprotokoll
                </td>
                <td>
                    <code>http://<i>localhost:4444</i>/show_log?job=<i>jobname</i></code>
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>
                    Taskprotokoll
                </td>
                <td>
                    <code>http://<i>localhost:4444</i>/show_log?task=<i>task_id</i></code>
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>
                    Auftragsprotokoll
                </td>
                <td>
                    <code>http://<i>localhost:4444</i>/show_log?job_chain=<i>Job-Kette</i>&amp;order=<i>order_id</i></code>
                </td>
            </tr>
        </table>
    </p>
    <p>
        <i>localhost</i> ist <code>localhost</code> oder 127.0.0.1 oder der Name des Rechners, auf dem der Job Scheduler abläuft.
    </p>
    
    
    <h2>Job-Beschreibung</h2>
    <p>
        Die Job-Beschreibung aus <scheduler_element name="description"/> kann mit diesem URL abgerufen werden:
    </p>
    <p>
        <code>http://<i>localhost:4444</i>/job_description?job=<i>job</i></code>
    </p>
    <p>
        Die Beschreibung wird in HTML codiert erwartet.
    </p>
    <p>
    
    </p>
		
		
		
		<scheduler_keyword keyword="Web Interface"/>
		<scheduler_keyword keyword="User Interface"/>
		<scheduler_keyword keyword="GUI"/>
		<a href="user_interface"/>
		<h2>Built-In Graphical User Interface</h2>
		
		<p>
			The Job Scheduler can be operated using its own, built-in, web-based graphical user interface (GUI).
			Instructions for accessing this interface were provided in the 
			"<a href="http.xml">Operation&#160;with&#160;a&#160;Browser</a>" 
			section of this chapter (above).
		</p>
		
		<p>
			This interface is automatically installed and updated with the Job Scheduler installation package.
		</p>
		
		<p>
			The Job Scheduler GUI is configured in the <code>custom.js</code> file, 
			which is to be found in the <code>Job Scheduler installation directory\config\html</code> directory
		</p>
		
		<p>
			This interface is intended for the <em>operation</em> of the Job Scheduler
			- i.e. starting, monitoring and stopping the Job Scheduler itself, jobs &amp; job chains, orders, and 
			  any locks and Job Schedulers operating in a cluster.
			<br/>
			This interface should not be confused with the <a href="scheduler_editor.xml">Job Scheduler Editor</a>,
			which is a GUI used to <em>configure</em> the Job Scheduler itself, jobs &amp; job chains, orders using XML.
	<!--(Note that the Job Scheduler Documentation Editor can be called up from the Job Scheduler GUI. This is described below.)-->
			<br/>
			The Job Scheduler GUI should also not be confused with the Managed Jobs Administration interface, 
			which is a part of the Job Scheduler <em>Managed Jobs</em> package.
			The Managed Jobs Administration interface is a GUI for the creation and monitoring jobs, job chains &amp; orders and 
			comes with a user administration. 
			Further information about the Managed Jobs Administration interface can be found in the »Managed Jobs Documentation«.
		</p>
		
		<p>
			When first opened, the Job Scheduler GUI appears as shown in the screenshot below and
			comprises three areas:
		</p>
		
		<ul>
			<li>
				An upper menu bar, where the general configuration of the interface (language &amp; update) is carried out; 
				any monitoring functions the Job Scheduler is to carry out are shown and
				the configuration of the Job Scheduler itself in the 
				<a href="konfiguration.xml">XML configuration file</a> is shown.
				<br/>
				Note that here the XML configuration file is shown "read-only" - 
				to change the configuration, the <a href="scheduler_editor.xml">Job Scheduler Editor</a> or an alternative XML editor should 
				be used which has access to the Job Scheduler installation directory.
			</li>
			<li>
				A central menu and status bar, providing access to the most important Job Scheduler menus and 
				status information about the operation of the Job Scheduler.
				<br/>
				The "Update periodically" checkbox and the "Update" button are used to update the information shown 
				in the web interface either at regular intervals (when the checkbox is selected) or manually, 
				as required (using the button).
				The interval with which the regular updates of the interface are carried out is set 
				using the Settings dialog, which is accessed via the "Extras" button.
			</li>
			<li>
				A working area initially showing a list of the jobs configured for the Job Scheduler,
				which can be used to provide information about other aspects of the Job Scheduler operation 
				such as the job chains, process classes and locks by selecting the appropriately named menu tabs.
				Note that, should, for example, no locks be configured then the "Locks" menu tab will not be shown.
			</li>
		</ul>
		
		<img class="screen_shot" src="images/job_scheduler_http_gui_reduced.jpg"/>
		
		<p>
			The main menu for the operation of the Job Scheduler is shown in the next screenshot:
		</p>
		
		<img class="screen_shot" src="images/job_scheduler_http_menu_reduced.jpg"/>
		
		<p>
			Detailed information about the state of one of the jobs listed in the main working area of the interface 
			can be obtained by clicking on the name of the job.
			This causes the right hand part of this area to divide and 
			additional areas  showing status information about the job, about the task and about the taks queue to be displayed 
			as can be seen in the screen shot below:
		</p>
		
		<img class="screen_shot" src="images/job_scheduler_http_joblist_details_reduced.jpg"/>
		
		<p>
			The job status area also contains a menu providing the main commands necessary for controlling the job
			as shown in the next screen shot:
		</p>
		
		<img class="screen_shot" src="images/job_scheduler_http_job_menu_reduced.jpg"/>
		
		<p>
			The "Show description" item in the menu opens a new browser window containing the job description.
			Job descriptions such as the one shown below can be written with the Job Editor.
			This editor combines documentation of the job, its configuration and a generate function, 
			where the job can be newly generated after changes to its configuration have been made.
			It is so integrated in the Job Scheduler installation that the Job Scheduler automatically 
			takes account of changes in a job configuration without having to be restarted.
		</p>
		
		<p>
			The documentation for the Job Editor can be read in the 
			<link href="http://www.sos-berlin.com/doc/de/scheduler_editor/sos_help.htm">Job Documentation Editor</link>
			tutorial.
		</p>
		
		<img class="screen_shot" src="images/job_scheduler_http_job_description_reduced.jpg"/>
		
		<p>
			Information about tasks carrying out a job is shown in the task area of the interface as 
			shown in the next screen shot:
		</p>
		
		<img class="screen_shot" src="images/job_scheduler_http_task_reduced.jpg"/>
		
		<p>
			A task menu is provided as shown in the following screen shot:
		</p>
		
		<img class="screen_shot" src="images/job_scheduler_http_task_menu_reduced.jpg"/>
		
		<p>
			Information about any errors occuring in the execution of a job is shown in the interface job area:
		</p>
		
		<img class="screen_shot" src="images/job_scheduler_http_task_error_reduced.jpg"/>
		
		<p>
			If the Job Scheduler is part of a Job Scheduler cluster, providing backup, monitoriung and fail-over features, 
			a corresponding "Cluster" menu tab will be shown in the main working area of the interface.
			As can be seen in the next screen shot, a button is provided to a menu for configuring cluster related aspects of the 
			Job Scheduler operation:
		</p>
		
		<img class="screen_shot" src="images/job_scheduler_http_backup_reduced.jpg"/>
		
		<p>
			The principles for using the Job Scheduler GUI and 
			which have been described in conjunction with the features shown in the preceeding screen shots
			are followed for the aspects of the interface which have not been shown in the screen shots.
			This means, for example, that use of the job chain part of the interface should follow intuitively.
		</p>
		
		<p>
			Detailed information about the configuration and operation of the Job Scheduler can be found 
			in the following sections of this documentation:
		</p>
		
		<ul>
			<li>
				The <a href="konfiguration.xml">XML Configuration</a> of the Job Scheduler.
			</li>
			<li>
				<a href="job.xml">Jobs and Job Chains</a>.
			</li>
			<li>
				<a href="order.xml">Orders</a>.
			</li>
			<li>
				<a href="protokolle.xml">Log files and errors</a>.
			</li>
			<li>
				<a href="messages/index.xml">Error messages</a>.
			</li>
		</ul>
		
</description>
