<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- $Id$ -->

<?xml-stylesheet href="api-default_language.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>


<api.class
    name        = "javax-Log"
    object_name = "logger"
    base_dir    = "../"
    author      = "$Author: ss $"
    date        = "$Date: 2012-06-12 21:42:49 +0200 (Di, 12 Jun 2012) $"
>

<title>
    Logger
<!--Prookollierung-->
</title>

<description>
    <p>
      The java plugin for running script-jobs produce some log messages for analyzing purposes.
      Thus we use <a href="http://logging.apache.org/log4j/">log4j</a> for logging, it is possible to configure it via a properties file.
    </p>
    
    <p>
      The messages of the script itself will be forwarded to this logger instance, too. To point up
      this fact we provide a special object named <i>logger</i> to each script. It is an instance of
      <i>org.apache.log4j.Logger</i>, that means that you can configure your log with all capabilities
      of log4j appenders.
    </p>
    
    <p>
      It is still possible to use the <a href="Log.xml">spooler_log</a> object (the internal logging service of JS), but it is
      <b>not recommended</b>, because it will not supported in future versions of the JS.
    </p>
    
    <p>
      The assumption for using a log4j properties file for the job scheduler is that it is placed in the
      classpath of the JVM. You can configure the classpath in the scheduler configuration file
      factory.ini.
    </p>
    
    <p>
      If you want to redirect the log messages into the task log of the running job you have to use
      the special appender <i>com.sos.JSHelper.Logging.BufferedJobSchedulerLog4JAppender</i>
      build for JobScheduler. The following sample will show a log4j configuration for this
      purpose:
      <pre>
# assign the appender for the scripting-api
# please notice: if appender scheduler is used the log-entries of the class
# will be placed in the task-log of the scheduler job
log4j.logger.com.sos.scheduler.engine.kernel.scripting=debug, scheduler
log4j.appender.scheduler=com.sos.JSHelper.Logging.BufferedJobSchedulerLog4JAppender
log4j.appender.scheduler.layout=org.apache.log4j.PatternLayout
log4j.appender.scheduler.layout.ConversionPattern=%5p [%t] (%F:%L) - %m%n
      </pre>
    </p>

</description>

<example programming_language="javax.script">
    <pre>logger.info( "Something for the Log" );</pre>
</example>

</api.class>
